No, you did not misread that title. We
are still talking about westward
expansion, but this time it's all about
the social and cultural effects that it
had. And no small part of that includes
significant conflicts with all the folks
who already lived in the West. So, if
you're ready to get them brain cows
milked, let's get to it. Okay, so as a
quick refresher from the last video,
Americans migrated westward for all
sorts of reasons, but most of those
reasons can be summed up thusly. They
wanted to achieve self-sufficiency and
independence. And as they migrated, it
seemed to be at long last the
fulfillment of Thomas Jefferson's vision
of an agrarian America filled with
farmers working their own land and
needing no intervention from no one, not
least the government. But as I talked
about in the last video, westward
migration during this period would not
have been possible at this scale if it
hadn't been for big daddy [music]
government giving away land and footing
the bill. Regardless, one thing all
these migrants had in common was that
their movement was in large part
facilitated by the rapidly expanding
railroad network that connected the east
to the west. There are two groups of
migrants that illustrate this trend that
you're going to need to know. Oh, and by
the way, if you want note guys to follow
along with this video and all my videos,
check that link in the description.
Anyway, the first group of migrants to
know were called the exodusters. Now,
remember that all of this migration is
occurring during reconstruction. And
that means that in the southern states,
the white leadership is trying its
absolute hardest to marginalize black
Americans and to recreate the social
conditions that they had before the war.
And that meant, among other things, that
black Americans were subject to
increasing amounts of violence and
brutality from groups like the Kulux
Clan. Therefore, not surprisingly, a
large group of black farmers in the
south banded together to purchase land
in Kansas. And they left the South in a
massive migration. And so, they call
themselves the Exodusters, in a nod to
the Jews in the Old Testament that
escaped slavery in Egypt in an event
known as the Exodus. Anyway, throughout
the 1880s, something like 40,000 of them
settled in Kansas to establish
homesteads apart from the oppressive
racial atmosphere in the south. And they
encountered the same environmental
difficulties that I mentioned in the
last topic, and many of their farms
failed as a result. However, their
movement sparked a significant
geographic reorganization of black
Americans from the south to the west,
and that was kind of a big deal. And
then the second group of migrants to
know are the homesteaders. These were
the Americans who migrated west in
response to the passage of the Homestead
Acts of 1862, which promised 160 acres
of free land to anyone who would live
there for 5 years and improve it. Now,
they saw westward migration as an
opportunity to achieve self-sufficiency
and independence. And since I talked a
lot about them in the last video, we'll
leave it there. Well, okay, now it's
time to crank up the tension. You see,
for a whole lot of reasons, the western
frontier was often portrayed as a
pristine and empty land just yearning
for American habitation. But as it
turned out, a whole lot of people
already lived there, like various
American Indian groups in the Great
Plains and Mexican-Americans in the
Southwest. And as more and more American
migrants moved into the West, that
caused a sharp competition for land and
an increase of tensions between white
settlers, American Indians, and
Mexican-Americans. And let's start with
conflicts among Mexican-Americans. Now,
recall from the last unit that the
Mexican-American War ended with the
signing of the Treaty of Guadalupe
Hidalgo in 1848. And in that treaty, the
US agreed to make all Mexicans living in
the land that made up the Mexican
session American citizens. Now, a good
number of those who became
Mexican-Americans owned large farms and
ranches. And with white American
migrants pouring into the territory and
laying their own claims to that land,
tensions mounted rapidly. And when those
conflicts came before the courts, judges
often sided with the white settlers and
stripped Mexican-Americans of their
land. Therefore, not surprisingly, some
of these Mexican-American citizens
mounted a fierce resistance. For
example, let me introduce you to a
vigilante group known as Las Goras
Blancas, which when being translated
means the white hats. And so, with their
white hats on, these fighters raided the
farms of white Americans and cut down
their fences and destroyed their
property. Well, okay, now let's turn to
conflicts created by westward movement
with respect to American Indians. Now,
over the course of the 19th century,
westward migrating Americans had put
more and more pressure on various
American Indian groups to evacuate lands
that were desirable to white settlers.
And sometimes American Indians resisted
violently, but other times they
capitulated to the overwhelming force of
the US military. And as a result, much
of the indigenous balance of power in
the west had shifted to groups like the
Sue, who were by nature a mobile nation.
So all that sets the stage for one of
the most significant reasons for
conflicts among this group. And that
would be the US's almost constant
breaking of treaties with American
Indian nations. So near the beginning of
the massive American migration beyond
the Mississippi River, the US government
signed the Treaty of Fort Laram with a
group of American Indian nations. And
this treaty acknowledged that these
nations were sovereign and autonomous,
but also confined them to certain
portions of land that would be off
limits to American settlers. Wink. And
yeah, it was the same story we've
already heard over and over throughout
this course. When white settlers
discovered valuable mineral resources on
American Indian land, or when they
simply wanted the land for farming, they
took what they desired with no regard
for the legality of what they did. And
despite the agreements of the US
government to protect American Indian
land from white encroachment, these
settlers were almost never stopped or
prosecuted under the terms of the two
treaties of Fort Laramie. So not
surprisingly, this development led to
violent conflicts between the US and
American Indian nations. And I'll give
you two related examples. First, we have
the Sand Creek Massacre in 1864. So
during the Civil War, Americans in the
West began to get real twitchy and
paranoid that the Sue and Cheyenne would
attack them while they were distracted
with the war. And therefore, some
Americans began to call for US military
campaigns against American Indians in
order to neutralize the potential
threat. And so, in 1864, the chief of
the Cheyenne named Black Kettle began to
suspect that his people will be attacked
without any provocation on their part.
So, Black Kettle raised his concern to
several US agents who instructed him to
lead his people to settle along Sand
Creek in Colorado so that they could
sign a treaty guaranteeing their safety.
But instead, the Colorado militia showed
up by surprise and slaughtered over a
hundred women and children while the men
were away on a hunt. That act provoked
an instant and violent reaction from the
Cheyenne and their allies, the Sue. They
responded by attacking white settlements
in the area and burning houses to the
ground, which set off a series of
conflicts known as the Sue Wars. Now,
the US military arrived to fight, but
failed to subdue the Sue, who countered
with a massacre of their own, killing 80
US soldiers in the wilderness of
Wyoming. And so, the conflicts lasted
until 1890 when American Indian
resistance was finally snuffed out by
American military force. Now, in light
of all this violence and resistance,
reform-minded American policymakers were
now confronted with two opposing
problems. First, there seemed to be no
halting the flow of American migration
westward. Second, in the face of such a
flood of migrants, there was no way to
continue honoring US treaties protecting
American Indian land and their
sovereignty. Therefore, these
policymakers decided that the only way
to prevent further conflict while
upholding American Indians themselves
was to assimilate them to American
society. In other words, if American
Indians became like white people, then
they would be better for it. and the
conflicts generated by westward
expansion would cease. And policymakers
justified this belief on the conviction
that indigenous Americans didn't use
their land properly anyway and therefore
they were just wasting its potential.
And so there were two major efforts made
by the US toward assimilating American
Indians. First was the DAW act which was
passed in 1887 and it mandated two major
developments. First, the law officially
ended the federal government's
recognition of American Indian
sovereignty over their own land. Second,
it divided up reservation lands into
160acre plots and allowed the heads of
American Indian households to farm the
land. Additionally, if they did so for
25 years, the American Indians would
become American citizens. However, that
citizenship offer came with a
significant caveat. Namely, that they
were required to abandon their ancestral
culture, including their religion and
their language and their customs. In
other words, American Indians could
become citizens if they fully
assimilated to white American culture.
And the government believed that this
would actually improve their lives. And
then the second major push for
assimilation came in the form of
boarding schools, which would provide an
environment in which American Indian
children could learn to become American.
For example, the Carile Indian
Industrial School was established in
Pennsylvania in 1879. And over the
course of a few decades, thousands of
American Indian children were enrolled.
And the school's founder had a motto
that paints the entire picture of what
these schools were about. He said, "Kill
the Indian, save the man." In other
words, these schools sought to strip
everything that was Indian from these
children so that the real human being
underneath could finally emerge. And so,
to that end, children were required to
speak English and were given American
names and dressed in American clothing.
And there were many other schools like
this one. And combined with the effects
of the DAW act, US Indian policy had
devastating effects on the preservation
of American Indian culture.
Additionally, these children were often
abused and many ended up dying and being
buried in unmarked mass graves. Now, in
response to this enormous pressure to
assimilate along with the pile of broken
treaties and violent conflicts in the
west, a massive effort to resist emerged
among American Indians. It was known as
the ghost dance and it spread throughout
the western plains starting in 1888. It
originated with an indigenous prophet
named Wavoka. And he had a vision that
American Indians would drive the white
invaders out from indigenous lands and
that in order to accomplish such a feat,
American Indians must participate in the
ghost dance which would raise their
ancestors from the dead and help them to
fight and eventually return to their
traditional ways. So the prophecy and
the dance spread quickly across the
northern plains where it was taken up by
thousands of Lakota soup. Now the US
military believed this movement to be a
sign that American Indian resistance was
gathering steam yet again. And so in
1890 they rode out to crush the
rebellion. They met 300 Sue performing
the dance at Wounded Knee Creek in South
Dakota and opened fire on the dancers.
And in the end they killed something
like 250 Sue, many of them women and
children. And so what became the Wounded
Knee Massacre represented the final
major effort of American Indian
resistance to westward expansion and
assimilation. And by 1890, Congress
would officially declare the frontier to
be settled. But it settlement came at an
enormous cost. Okay, you can click here
to watch my other videos from unit 6 or
you can click here to grab my video note
guides which are going to help you get
all the contents of this course firmly
crammed into your brain fold. I'm glad
you came around and I'll catch you on
the flipflop.